and today we are going to dive into the
world of building web browser extensions
making extensions is not only incredibly
fun but super easy to do you can make
browser extensions as a side projects
just for fun to build something useful
for you and your friends or you can even
build whole businesses around them like
many companies have done by using the
browser as a distribution Channel you
can reach millions of users worldwide
and make an impact on how they interact
with the web extensions are also super
easy to install which means a higher
adoption rate and they also offer an
incredible level of integration they
allow you to enhance and modify your
users browsing experience with features
that work seamlessly with the websites
they visit there are two kinds of
extensions we can make pop-up extensions
and code injecting extensions pop-up
extensions are designed to display a
small user interface that appears when
and the user clicks on the extensions
icon on the browser's toolbar these
pop-ups contain a Mini web page built
with HTML CSS and JavaScript they are
perfect for providing quick access to
specific functionality or information
without requiring users to navigate away
from the current page on this category
we have extensions like pocket an
extension that lets you save articles
videos and other content to read or
watch later even offline to do is an
extension that helps you manage your
to-do list and track your progress and
Forest an extension that helps you stay
focused and increase productivity by
using the popular technique of planting
virtual trees and avoiding distraction
code injecting extensions are where I
think things get more exciting for us
developers as they can unleash our
creativity code injecting extensions
modify the content or behavior of a web
page by injecting JavaScript CSS or HTML
into the page the this allows developers
to customize and enhance the
functionality of websites beyond what
the maker of the website originally
planned it opens up a world of
possibilities on creating powerful and
unique experiences with code injecting
extensions developers can dynamically
modify the page content add new features
and functionality and even integrate
with external apis on this category we
have extensions like unlock plus an
extension that prevents advertisement
from appearing on websites interestingly
the company responsible for developing
this extension reportedly earned more
than 55 million euros last year a dark
reader an extension that allows users to
inject custom CSS to enable dark mode on
web pages refined GitHub an extension
that enhances the GitHub interface with
added features improvements and time
saving shortcuts for a better user
experience what font an easy to use
extension that identifies fonts used on
any web page giving designers and
typography enthusiasts quick access to
font information honey a shopping
extension that automatically applies
coupon codes to your online purchases
saving you money grammarly a popular
extension that checks your writing for
spelling and grammatical errors
suggesting corrections as you type and
my favorite one language reactor this
extension completely modified the way
the Netflix player looks like for people
that are learning a second language it
transforms the Netflix player by adding
features like dual subtitles interactive
transcripts and build in dictionary it
also allows you to create an account to
save words and set your vocabulary level
as well to show you how easy and good it
is to make browser extensions on this
video we are going to make an extension
that I named katify this extension is
going to be both a pop-up extension and
a code injecting extension here is how
katify works first it will show you some
cat food photos and when we choose a
photo the extension will set that photo
as the background for every website we
visit let's get started by going to an
empty folder and creating the most
important file that an extension will
have
manifest.json this file will tell
browsers while your extension is about
it will ask for permissions it will
register the code to be injected and it
will register the pop-up to be opened
when the user clicks on our
manifest.json we are going to write the
name of the extension the description
and the version as well as the paths to
the icons of the extension on 16 32 48
and 128 pixel sizes this is the icon of
the extension that I created before
using mid journey to test the extension
in Chrome we are going to go to the
Chrome menu then select more tools and
click on extensions next we will enable
developer mode and click on load
unpacked extension finally we will
navigate to the folder containing the
extension files and select the folder to
load it into Chrome as you can see the
manifest.json file is being read showing
us the name description and icon of the
extension next to the other extensions
we installed before so far our extension
does not do anything to change that
we're first going to build the pop-up
that will show up when the user clicks
the extension icon next to the URL bar
we're going to expand our manifest.json
to include this code here we are telling
the browser that our extension has an
action when clicked we tell the browser
what icon and title to show and we also
provide the path to a file called
popup.html that will be inside of a
pop-up folder that HTML file will have
an H1 and many images along with a bit
of CSS that you don't need to see for
now after we save that file and reload
the extension we will be able to see the
icon and name of the extension on the
Chrome toolbar indicating that our
extension is active and ready for use
when we click on the icon the pop up
that we just created will be displayed
as you can see we can click on the cats
but when we do nothing happens to change
that we are going to import a script
called popup.js from our
pop-up.html our pop-up.js will know when
an image of a cat is clicked and when it
is it is going to save that choice on
the user's disk to be able to save data
on the disk of the user as an extension
we have to ask for a storage permission
to do this all we have to do is add the
permissions keyword to our manifest now
in our pop-up.js file we are going to
grab all the images and for each one of
them we are going to listen for click
event and when the click happens we are
going to save the image URL to the
storage of the browser having enabled
the user to select a cut and now that we
are saving their choice we now have to
write the code that will load that
choice and put the cut as a background
image of the page to inject the code on
each website we go to we have to modify
our manifest.json file a bit here we are
saying that on any URL the user goes to
we want to inject the file located on
the folder scripts named inject.js the
code of inject.js is super simple first
we search for the image key that we
saved before when the user chose the cut
if we find it we set it as the
background image of the body of the page
we set it to 200 pixels and we make it
repeat and now after we reload the
extension and select a cut everywhere we
go our code will be injected on every
page which will change the background to
the cut and we're done we successfully
build the catify extension that will
work on Google Chrome Microsoft Edge
Opera Brave neverwell and even Firefox
with a few modifications as you saw it
is very easy and fun to make browser
extensions we can do almost whatever we
can think of on the browser of the user
sir and the pages they visit as with I
hope you enjoyed following along with
this tutorial and learn something new if
you found this video useful please
consider liking it and subscribing to
the channel let me know in the comments
if you have built a browser extension
before or if you have an idea of
something you want to build and don't
forget that if you want to learn things
like JavaScript python react react
native go dark flutter among many others
for absolutely free all you have to do
is click the link below to join any of
our many free courses that you can take
right now for absolutely free with me
only though
see you on the next one bye
[Music]
thank you